<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linux on Jacob Hell's Blog</title><link>https://jacobhell.github.io/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in linux on Jacob Hell's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jacobhell.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Programming on the Cheap. How to Program on a $20 Device.</title><link>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/programming-on-the-cheap/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/programming-on-the-cheap/</guid><description>&lt;p>Like most people, I like to do things as cheaply as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This thought extends to programming for me. Lucky for us who are software developers, a lot of the tools we get to use are free.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This includes programming languages with their compilers, IDEs and editors, and even operating systems. We can thank the pioneers of the
free software movement and GNU project for this.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="text-align:center">&lt;img src="../../535px-Heckert_GNU_white.svg.png" alt="GNU logo" width="300" height="300">&lt;/div>
&lt;p>However, one thing we can&amp;rsquo;t get for free is the computer that we write, compile, and run our programs on. Not only are computers not
free, they can be very expensive! In fact, on &lt;a href="https://www.techradar.com/news/best-laptop-for-programming#8-asus-chromebook-flip">TechRadar&lt;/a>, the &amp;ldquo;affordable&amp;rdquo; option is the Asus Chromebook Flip. This machine retails for &lt;strong>$579&lt;/strong>! If I was non developer looking to get into programming, I would be out almost &lt;strong>$600&lt;/strong> before a single stroke of the keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Knowing this, I decided to pop into my local thrift store and see if there was a remedy for this insanity. That&amp;rsquo;s when I found this beauty:&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="text-align:center">&lt;img src="../../laptop1.jpg" alt="Laptop found at thrift store" width="300" height="300">&lt;/div>
&lt;p>A gently used Dell Inspiron E1405 was in the technology section screaming my name. I looked at the price tag, only &lt;strong>$20&lt;/strong>! What a steal! I quickly took out an Andrew Jackson and made off like a bandit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I got home, turned it on, and realized it had Windows XP on it:&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="text-align:center">&lt;img src="../../laptop2.jpg" alt="Laptop with windows xp" width="300" height="300">&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I have no desire to program on a computer with an operating system that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in over a decade. That&amp;rsquo;s where Linux comes in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now this was an old laptop, so I wanted to use a lightweight operating system on it. I ultimately chose Lubuntu, because it has LxQt, one of the lightest desktop graphical systems around. And I generally spend my time in the terminal emulator and vim, so I didnt&amp;rsquo;t need too many out of the box features.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lubuntu has a pretty straightforward &lt;a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Lubuntu/InstallingLubuntu">installation process&lt;/a>. I had no problems going through the steps in the guide. I did mistakenly try using the 64 bit version instead of the 32 bit version, which is what the cpu required.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could have avoided this though, if I looked it up beforehand: &lt;a href="https://www.computerhope.com/issues/ch001121.htm">How to check&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the stress and anxiety of $600 laptops behind me, I was able to fire up my new to me Lubuntu powered laptop, and write this blog post with great amounts of joy and happiness.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="text-align:center">&lt;img src="../../hacking_on_lubuntu.png" alt="Laptop using Lubuntu" width="600" height="450">&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>