<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>productivity on Jacob Hell's Blog</title><link>https://jacobhell.github.io/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in productivity on Jacob Hell's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jacobhell.github.io/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Use uBlock Origin to Limit Distractions</title><link>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/u-block-distraction/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/u-block-distraction/</guid><description>&lt;p>uBlock Origin is usually used to block unwanted ads. But it is also a powerful tool to increase productivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like most people, I get distracted by shiny things easily. By &amp;ldquo;Shiny Things&amp;rdquo;, I mean interesting headlines, news articles, and videos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m different though, because I know that I need to block the shiny things before my feeble human brain can see them. Luckily, I know of just the tool to help me.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ublock-origin">uBlock Origin&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The author and maintainer of uBlock Origin, Raymond Hill, is dedicated to privacy. Unlike other ad blocking services, uBlock specifically refuses donations and &amp;ldquo;Approved Ads&amp;rdquo;. So you have no reason to worry that things will get unblocked.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-problem-i-had">The Problem I Had&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>So I have a website that I go on frequently. It is called &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/">StackOverflow&lt;/a>. It is a question and answer site for programming and computer problems. It is a part of a larger question and answer site called &lt;a href="https://stackexchange.com/">StackExchange&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately for those distracted by shiny things, StackOverflow has a &amp;ldquo;Hot Network Questions&amp;rdquo; section. This section has posts from other parts of StackExchange. The questions posted here are often very interesting, and they are difficult to resist clicking on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s an example:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="../../network_posts.png" alt="The bane of my existence">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As far as I know, there is no way to hide this section. Even if you have a StackOverflow account.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="blocking-distracting-things">Blocking Distracting Things&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s easy to block distracting things using uBlock Origin. Watch the gif below:&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="text-align:center">&lt;img src="../../blocking_network_posts.gif" alt="blocking network posts gif" width="800" height="600">&lt;/div>
&lt;p>I hope this helped on your quest to reduce distractions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Flow: How Working from Home Has Made Me Productive</title><link>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/flow/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jacobhell.github.io/post/flow/</guid><description>&lt;p>Working from home has been a boon for my productivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to work from home since, well I started working. I&amp;rsquo;m introverted and dislike interruptions. I&amp;rsquo;m not good at small talk. I control the air conditioning. The reasons are endless.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the pandemic started, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working from home. I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed the reasons I listed above. However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be extremely productive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I find myself most productive when in a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">state of flow&lt;/a>. In this state, I really only notice myself and the monitor. The keyboard is just an extension of myself. No bug deters me. Unfortunately, I only attain this state for around 30 minutes in the office. This is due to a combination of interruptions and not being in complete control my environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, I can wear whatever clothes I want. If my head or eyes hurt, I can just go lay in bed for 10 minutes. If the lights are too bright, I can dim them. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do that onsite.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Managing interruptions while working from home is easier. I only check my email 3 times per day at 8 am, 12 pm, and 4 pm. My phone number is available to members of my team, but I have the choice of answering calls. If called when I&amp;rsquo;m in a state of deep flow, I can text back that I&amp;rsquo;m not available. Then call when it works for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This might seem mean. But I&amp;rsquo;ve found most urgent emails and calls are not urgent. This is what Cal Newport (one of my favorite authors) thinks about &lt;a href="https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2008/02/15/fixed-schedule-productivity-how-i-accomplish-a-large-amount-of-work-in-a-small-number-of-work-hours/">keeping a fixed schedule&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>I’m not available.&lt;/strong> I often work in hidden nooks of the various libraries on campus. I check and respond to work e-mail only a few times a day. People have to wait for responses from me. It’s often hard to find me. Sometimes they get upset at first. But they don’t really need immediate access. And I will always respond within a reasonable timeframe and get them what they need. So they adjust. And I get things done.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>With complete control over my environment and no interruptions, I have averaged 4 hours of flow per day! It&amp;rsquo;s probably the most productive I&amp;rsquo;ve been in my life.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>